<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A word of advertisement &amp; advice to the godly in Scotland by a Scotch man, and a cordiall vvelwisher to the interests of the godly in Scotland, both in civils and spirituals.</title>
            <author>Scotch man and a cordial wel-wisher to the interest of the godly in Scotland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3553</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23487</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12765121</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12765121</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93569</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67049)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93569)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 994:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A word of advertisement &amp; advice to the godly in Scotland by a Scotch man, and a cordiall vvelwisher to the interests of the godly in Scotland, both in civils and spirituals.</title>
                  <author>Scotch man and a cordial wel-wisher to the interest of the godly in Scotland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93569:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93569:1"/>
            <p>A WORD OF Advertiſement &amp; Advice TO THE GODLY IN SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>By a <hi>Scotch</hi> Man, and a Cordiall VVel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſher to the Intereſt of the Godly in <hi>Scotland,</hi> both in CIVILS and SPIRITUALS.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Words in ſeaſon are like apples of gold in pictures of ſilver.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Open rebuke is better then ſecret love: Faithfull are the wounds of a Friend, but the kiſſes of an enemy are deceitfull.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:93569:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93569:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing deſirous (in this hour of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſad tryall and trouble) to be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to you, my dear Friends in the Lord, being amazed and aſtoniſhed to ſee you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter twelve or fourteen years Remonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Petitioning, and theſe backed with your ſw rds in your hand, againſt King, Parliament and Committees and indeed the whole Authorities of the Land for your juſt freedome and Liberties in Spiritual and Civil things; I ſay, to ſee the reſult of ſuch a buſineſs to be as it is this day; Is that which ſhould put all the People of God in this Land, upon the tryall and enquiry after the cauſes of this (I may ſay) your being ſo ſtrangely deſerted of God. And that I may, as your Chriſtian Friend, be helpful to you in this, I ſhall go back to the beginning of theſe great Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, and ſhall go along with you in ſo much of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of buſineſs to this day, as I have either been a witneſs unto, or can truly inform my ſelf of, at leaſt ſo much of them as may make it appear, what hath been your former practices, and the principles and ends carrying you on in theſe; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the buſineſs is ſoweighty, and you ſo much concern'd, and I ſo unfit to meddle therewith, I ſhall therefore beg of the Lord (that where I may miſtake matter of Fact, or ſhall come ſhort of the full repreſenting thereof) that ye (who may be better acquainted with the whole of Affairs then my ſelf) may deal ſo ingenuouſly with your ſelves, as to follow out your own knowledge and experiences in theſe; And more to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what I drive at, than what I ſpeak in particulars, which, I ſay, is to be helpful to you in your ſearch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear Freind,</hi> Ye may remember that in the beginning of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93569:3"/>this weighty buſineſs, that which did engage you the people of God (for to you onely I ſpeak) was your being oppreſſed in your conſciences in ſpiritual things by the King, and thoſe employed by him, and the connivance and concurrance of theſe that were the Repreſentative of Church and State, together with the Tyranny and Oppreſſions exerciſed over your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Eſtates in ſeveral things; to be freed of theſe, the attaining, eſtabliſhing and increaſe of juſt Freedom in both theſe, was that which chiefly did engage you in the Work: There were many that did go on upon corrupt principles and ends, whom the Lord made uſe of for the time, and diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many of them ſince (and will more) that they were not, nor are ſuitable Inſtruments for carrying on of ſuch a Work: And though many of your ſelves did not diſtinctly and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly conceive what was the intereſt of the buſineſs you were engaged for at firſt; yet theſe who ſaw a far off, knew much of it in the time: And theſe who were the people of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, found and held it forth as their duty, to be carried on by the Providences of the Lord, to many things in which they were matterially engaged, that they did not at firſt clearly apprehend in particulars: And ſo all along every new diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of duty, in the taking away of any thing that did appear to be inconſiſtant with the being or wel-being of that which ye had primarily engaged your ſelves unto (or the eſtabliſhing of any thing that might advance it) did make manifeſt the rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of more or fewer mers principles in engaging therein, by their falling off, or becoming Enemies to it: And how often have I heard it preached, That this work would have none to follow it, but ſuch as were truly godly, and that every corrupt man would fall off from it, when the true intereſt of the work did not conſiſt with his corrupt intereſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> Be pleaſed to conſider the riſe of this great buſineſs; Were not many of you panting after, praying for it, years before it came? Were there not private perſons in the beginning that did own it againſt the King, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of the Nation? The ſtate of the cauſe being as it was, could any be friends to it, but ſuch as were truly godly? Or could any firſt or laſt own it, without a contradiction, but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93569:3"/>ſuch? And hath not your experience all along made this evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent unto you, that both Perſons and Intereſts which (at firſt) you thought might be ſutable for the buſineſs, and might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with it, have proved otherwiſe? Have not they either left you, or you them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the beginning,</hi> it was thought by ſome, that it was enough to be afraid of the Service-Book; But how miſerable had you ſtil bin, if the Lord had ſuffered you to reſt there, or had inclined the Kings heart to grant it; and how far ſhort had it been of thoſe farther degrees of juſt freedom, the Lord hath ſince car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried you out to the owning of, and adventuring for, let your conſciences tell you: And ſo all along adhering to this founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to wit (the freeing your ſelves from Oppreſsions in your Conſciences, Perſons and Eſtates, and the eſtabliſhing and carrying on your juſt freedom in theſe, not (ſo much) as <hi>Scots</hi> men, as the people of God) ye have been carried on in wayes ye have not knovvn nor foreſeen, looking alwayes upon it as your duty (and practiſing it) and for it abandoning (or decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt) every perſon, intereſt, power, or authority in leſs or more, as they did prove inconſiſtant with the work or enemies to it, or retarders thereof, or inſuitable inſtruments: And I do appeal to your experience, (what ever thoughts you might have in the beginning) if it be coſiſtant with, that which is really and indeed the work of God either with its being or well being, Not to be in the hands of ſutable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments (I mean) ſuch as are really Godly, and mindes it upon that accompt: And if ſo? how much leſs can it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant with it, to be managed by a number of men, who are enemies to the Work, haters of you and the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, minding nothing but themſelves and their own intereſt, being underminers of the things they profeſs to maintain, and cannot be otherways: And indeed to my underſtanding, that which hath bin the conteſt for ſome years by-gone, hath much differed from (or rather let me ſay, exceeded) what it was in the beginning: at firſt the ſum of your Petitioning was to be freed from the Service-Book, and Book of Canons, afterwards ye ſlew ſo high as to ſtrike at the root, <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> and all that <hi>Roman</hi> Hierarchie; and for a long time the ſupplicating againſt theſe,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93569:4"/>the Coveranting againſt theſe, the defending your ſelves againſt ſuch as would continue theſe yokes upon you (with ſome ſmaller things which had relation to Civill Priviledges) ſeemed chiefly (if not wholly) to be the ſtate of the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell: Afterwards you were carried on further and further in owning what was neceſſary for advancing the great buſineſs you were engaged into, and diſ-owning what you ſaw de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to it, as the Kings Negative Vote in Parliament and Generall Aſſemblies, the uncertainty of the calling of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and eſtabliſhing a Committee of Eſtates in the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vales of Parliament, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But after all theſe were obtained by a wonderfull Series of Providence, carrying you along, and countenance you, being freed from the Service-Book, Epiſcopacy and the reſt, your Enemies being vanquiſhed, the powers of the Nation (in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance) friendly to you, and countenancing the buſines; the King, the great oppoſer thereof made in a manner to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove you in all you had done, by his ratifying all in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament; ſo that you could deſire nothing of him outwardly but you had it, Ordinances in purity, none to manage the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs but ſuch as were profeſſed Friends to the work; yet for all this were you not ſtil at a loſs, all you had gotten every day ready to be betrayed, every farther degree of freedom oppoſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear Friend,</hi> conſider (I conceive the ſtreſſe of the matter lyes here) that which has bin your hurt &amp; hinderance all along, hath been not ſo much open enemies as diſſembling prophane men among you, haters of godlines and the Godly, and of any appearance of God (in diſcovering of duties in order to the carrying on of the great Work, or in abandoning what was diſcovered to be inconſiſtent or incongruous therwith) engaged in the buſines upon corrupt accompts, ready alway to betray it into the hands of enemies, and while avowing themſelves, and continuing profeſſed Friends, oppoſing and retarding good motions, raiſing Factions againſt you, and the true intereſt of the cauſe, and by theſe great pretences and profeſſions of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Covenant and Work of God becoming ſo nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in Judicatories, that they have carryed all before them: I ſhall inſtance the year 1648. Did not that Parliament then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93569:4"/>become ſo highly Malignant, that many (if not all) that were Godly in the Parliament, (though I do not ſay that all who went along with them in the Proteſtation, did it upon a right accompt, as has appeared ſince) were forced to proteſt and leave the Houſe, and yet all the while none pretending more for the Cauſe of God and Covenant then they, while they were carrying on their Malignant Deſignes, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting all the Godly in <hi>Scotland,</hi> who did not go along with them. And indeed can you ſay but all along (though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times you have been more at one in carrying forward ſome outward thing) there has been reall and viſible diſtances and heart burnings betwixt you the Godly, and ſuch as were enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the buſineſſe upon a wrong accompt, they ſometimes whiſpering that good motions coming from you, did ſmell of Sectariſme and new light, or by raiſing Factions againſt you, to the dividing of Judicatories, and ſo at beſt clogging you in the way, and making the Work halt, to the ſadding of the Spirits of all honeſt men, that were looking on. So that I ſay, the great conteſt of late, and that which hath had a great influence upon all the late tranſactions, theſe five or ſix years, hath been by whoſe hands that ſo generally profeſſed, ſhould be managed, and who could juſtly and rightly claim an Intereſt in it as Friends, or ſutable inſtruments thereto, and who were enemies; I appeal to your own experience what was in this before the year 1648. how honeſt men were under-mined by a Faction, that partly had engaged with them in the beginning, and partly had crept in by profeſſing themſelves to go along with them in the Work, by taking the Covenant (which by the way I deſire you to take notice, whether it has not been to large a rule in ſo ſearching a buſines) did they not ſee themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermined a long time before it came to ſo direct a breach as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards it did, and yet they profeſſing themſelves Friends to the Covenant and Work, they could not be rid of them, till themſelves were ſhuffled to the door: And though theſe that did then proteſt, ſeemed to be unanimous in what they did in their ends moving them to it, and their principles carrying them on in it, &amp; all that did follow therupon, yet I dare appeal to ſuch of you as were then acquainted with buſines, if many
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93569:5"/>of theſe that did proteſt were not in their judgements for an engagement at that ſame time, and that their ſearing from it, was their ſeeing it chiefly carried on by ſuch as they judged to be enemies to their ruling of matters though profeſſed friends to the Work; the power of managing buſineſſes being likely to be eſtabliſhed in their hands. This I can averre from ſome of the Proteſters themſelves, that at a cloſe Committee of the chief of the Proteſters, it was reſolved to poſſeſſe <hi>Berwick,</hi> and <hi>Carlile,</hi> long e're it was ſurpriſed by Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> and that party.</p>
            <p>And though the way you were then neceſſitated to (you owning your ſelves at firſt, but as private men, and the party in <hi>Scotland</hi> riſen in Armes and ſtanding for the Covenant and intereſt of the people of God) was an extraordinary remedy, you being expreſly tied in the Covenant to maintain the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament, yet under that notion, and upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt that you were the People of God, and them that had onely the true intereſt to profeſs your ſelves Friends to the Cauſe, Covenant, and intereſt of the People of God, and ſuch as only could rightly challenge a priviledge to manage theſe and places of truſt in the Kingdom, and yet all this while you were nothing but private men, there being a Committee of Eſtates appointed, that you could not ſay, but they were lawfully conſtituted: they having eſtabliſhed the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Committee as the Authority of the Kingdom, in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terval of the Parliament; upon the foreſaid accompt &amp; of their evil managing of buſineſs, through their becoming enemies to the Work and people of God as you then thought you did riſe in Arms againſt them, and did not onely oppoſe their Authority, but did break them ſo, as to be no. Authority at all; and moreover, did conſtrain them to condeſcend that you ſhould be a Committee of Eſtates: Being thus a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, you did ſet down Rules for calling a new Parliament, you did (contrary to the Fundamental Laws of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whereby every Freeholder, having a Forty ſhilling Land hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en of the King, hath the priviledge to vote in chooſing Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, and to be choſen) debar any from voting in Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or being Elected, that had voted in Parliament to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93569:5"/>Engagement, 1648. or in the Committee of Eſtates, had taken the Oath for carrying on thereof, or had ſubſcribed the Bond for promoving the ſame, or had taken the Oath in Committees of ſhires for the advancing of it, or had given obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in an active way, to the Acts enjoyning the Levies, &amp;c. for carrying on the ſaid Engagement. I inſiſt the longer upon this, and do make all theſe digreſsions, that it may appear that it was onely by private men all this was done. It is ſaid, that they were proteſtors in Parliament, yet I think it is obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to any that underſtands, that though your Proteſtation was a teſtimony, and gave you the greater clearneſs to act againſt that againſt which you had born your teſtimony, yet it did not enſtate you in any condition of being a Judicatory, or Publique Perſons, you having leſt the Parliament upon your Proteſtation; and though ſome of you were appointed Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Committee of Eſtates, yet that ſame Parliament in that ſame Act did declare, That all who were nominated to be of that Committee, ſhould, at their firſt ſitting, take the Oath for the faithful carrying on of that Engagement, and otherwiſe, not to ſit or vote, nor have any place therein; moreover, thoſe that then you look'd upon as your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, having got by you to <hi>Sterling,</hi> and having taken in the Town, and routed your Forces there, and you being at <hi>Faw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk,</hi> and your men daily leaving you, and you becoming more and more inconſiderable, you did (that I may omit nothing ſo far as I can remember, that was matter of Fact, it being the chief part of my deſign to help you in your ſearch, by remembering you of all the ſeveral Tranſactions about and ſince that time) judge it neceſſary to invite the Engliſh Army to your aſsiſtance; and this (as I am informed) by the advice of the Kirk, though they had formerly, in their Pulpits and Remonſtrances, declared them to be an Army of Sectaries; And how uſeful their incomming was to you, and how they did carry themſelves, you may remember; and what was the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their deſires to the Committee of Eſtates (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they had met with from the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> yea and from many of your ſelves, as you may know in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars) neither deſiring recompence from you for the injuries
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93569:6"/>
               <hi>England</hi> and themſelves had received, nor deſiring greater ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity from you, but that you ſhould eſtabliſh the power of the Kingdom in the hands of honeſt and godly men, however prejudiced againſt them, and for the others, that they ſhould not be employed without <hi>Englands</hi> conſent.</p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding you were a party ſeparated from the reſt, upon ſo honeſt an accompt, and had taken ſuch extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary wayes; yet ſince it hath evidently appeared that ſome, if not many, if not the greateſt part, did proteſt in Parliament, and riſe in Arms, and proceed in the buſineſs upon unſound ends and principles, which did appear to ſuch of you as were acquainted with the buſineſs, and did ſee a far off, not long after they were re-eſtabliſhed in power, by their jealouſies of honeſt men, their laboring to get ſuch into Judicatories, and Armies, and places of Truſt, as would ſerve their corrupt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and their diſcountenancing and oppoſing of godly men; And ever ſince your diviſions and jealouſies have grown, the ſeed of the Serpent and of the women, hath diſtinctly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, even in that little handful, that ſeemed to be ſeparated for the Lord, and for his peoples intereſt; and how theſe have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarded you in your Progreſs (after ſolemn acknowledgements of miſcarriages in Omiſsions, and Commiſsons, and ſolemn En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements to duties) of advancing the power of godlineſs, in countenancing of it, and eſtabliſhing the power of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the hands of ſuch as were godly, and diſcountenancing and purging out ſuch as were otherwiſe. How they have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored to entangle you into the Yoke of Bondage you had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been ſerving under, how they have made you fall back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and how they have entangled and enſnared you and themſelves, and the Kingdom, in many ſorrows, is apparent this day to theſe that runs by, I chiefly mean in the whole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs with the King: Theſe men, though they were as buſie and forward for bringing in the Engliſh Army as any, and had as much intimacy with them, yet ſeeing their way which they did walk into in <hi>England,</hi> to be inconſiſtent with their intereſt (the chief of them being Lords) and being apprehenſive that the godly in <hi>Scotland</hi> might comply with that Intereſt of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93569:6"/>Levelling, at leaſt the Arbitrary and abſolute way of great men; and withal, the Miniſters being poſſeſſed with prejudices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as appehending them to be Enemies to them as Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, though indeed, (as appears onely to their Arbitrary way) in ſpiritual things, and there too much medling in Civil things, or at leaſt, that they are no great freinds to theſe, together with the Commiſsioners carrages at <hi>London;</hi> all theſe did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to procure, that notwithſtanding of all the former curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies received from them, within a few weeks after the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Armies going out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> there was nothing almoſt to be heard in Pulpits but the Army of Sectaries, the perfide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Murtherers, filthy Dreamers, Contemners of Authority, Razers of the foundations of Government, Alterers thereof contrary to the Covenant, and therefore perfideous Covenant-breakers; the Kirk muſt put out a Declaration to this, and the State approve it; and theſe that were look'd upon as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of your deliverance, whoſe aſſiſtance the Kirk themſelves thought fit to take in a few weeks before, may not be ſpoken of but with Indignation: Whereas when theſe things are examined which they did after they went out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> I ſuppoſe it will be found their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie was as great, that put them on to do theſe things, and the hazard as eminent to the intereſt of all the Godly in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> yea <hi>Scotland</hi> alſo, and of all they had been fighting for the fore-going year, as that which put you to riſe in Arms, and to do all that followed upon it in 1648. I ſhall for this onely inſtance, the Letter written by the chief Rulers in <hi>Scotland</hi> to the Principall Leaders of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, preſently after their departure out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> preſſing them to break the Treatie with the late King at the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> and that unleſs it were broken, all the Godly in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> would be ruined. And moreover, was there any more irregularitie in their proceedings then in yours, yea I offer it to your ſerious conſideration from what has been, and might be ſaid, if there were not more in yours then in theirs; Things being thus car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on, upon, and by the corrupt intereſt of Lords and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men their dependers, and the intereſt of the Miniſters, you the Godly were intangled and enſnared, and made to go along up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93569:7"/>fair pretences of duty &amp; conſcience, not ſeeing the deſigne of thoſe whoſe intereſt lay in the buſines. Upon the pretence of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the outing ſome members of the Parl. of <hi>England,</hi> is taken notice of as a breach of Covenant, notwithſtanding that the ſame Party had broken the Committee repreſenting the Parl. of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as is before expreſſed: And that our own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners had written home, that the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> were going on in a Treatie with the King, and were likely to cloſe in a way, wherewith they were diſ-ſatisfied, and that they had left out <hi>Scotlands</hi> intereſt. The proceedings againſt the King, &amp; the taking of his life muſt be alſo proteſted againſt, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his continued and confirmed obduredneſs in his ways, &amp; al the Juſtice the Covenant tyes to againſt Delinquents, and the execution of Juſtice upon ſeverals of our own acting only by vertue of his Commiſſions, and that he were himſelf oft by us declared a Murtherer, the grand Murtherer, guilty of all the Innocent blood had been ſhed in the three Kingdoms, &amp; that we had no ty upon us for the preſervation of his Perſon by the Covenant, otherwiſe then as in the defence and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Religion and Libertie. If it be objected, that they were not a free conſtituted Judicatory that did the thing, and ſo upon that accompt it was murther: Let it be conſidered up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame conſideration, if it may not be as ſtrongly cleared, that <hi>Iames Grahame,</hi> and all that died upon a Scaffold ſince 1648. were murthered, ſince it may be made appear, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſtrict accompt of the Lawes of this Nation, there has not been a free nor right conſtituted Parliament ſince 1648. as appeares by what is aforeſaid concerning the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting of the Parliament that ſat down the fourth of <hi>Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> 1649. As a dutie the King that now is, behooved to be proclaimed immediatly, though then engaged and running head-long in his Fathers ſteps, Commiſſioning Prince <hi>Rupert, Iames Grahaem, Ormond,</hi> making an open and avowed Peace with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, to which height his Father never came: Commiſſioners are ſent to him, and though at that time through the ſtrength of his paſſion to the way his heart was engaged unto, and the apparent hopes in <hi>Ireland</hi> (whether he alſo ſent his goods) he was kept from any ſeeming condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendence
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93569:7"/>to their deſires, Yea though they were exceedingly baffled and ſlighted; yet the Lords ſeeing no conſiſtencie at all betwixt thoſe in <hi>England,</hi> and their Prerogative Intereſt as Lords, and finding a ſpirit of levelling (as they named it) begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to break out, honeſt men beginning to think, and to make it appear they thought the Lords intereſt to be exorbitant and tyrannicall, and that the moſt of them were enemies to Pietie and pious men, and to motions tending to the countenancing of both, and that they were friends to the getting in, and keeping in naughtie men in places of truſt, with a deſign to uphold their intereſt and greatnes, and beginning then to look after their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie in thoſe things that great men had encroched upon them, theſe conſiderations though ſo ſlighted, as aforeſaid, did move them under the notion of duty to preſſe a ſecond addreſſe. In which many Godly men were enſnared by condeſcending unto it upon this attempt, that they were deſirous to ſhun the ſcandal of being complyers with theſe they called Sectaries, who had declared againſt Monarchy: hovv that buſineſs vvas carried on many of you know better then my ſelf. An Expreſs being ſent to the Iſle of <hi>Iarſey</hi> to the King, by his return a Treaty was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired at <hi>Breda;</hi> the King writing to the Committee of Eſtates (naming them ſo) which he had not formerly done, (though then only with a Proviſo in order to that Treaty:) The ſame day and place that the King wrote to the Committee of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, he did write to <hi>James Graham,</hi> relating the former Commiſsion given him to come into <hi>Scotland,</hi> giving him an accompt of all paſſages between him and them in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and preſſing him vigourouſly to proſecute the buſineſs, and the rather, becauſe he thought his coming to <hi>Orkney</hi> had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned the ſending of that ſecond addreſs unto him, and he was hopefull his vigourous proſecuting of that which he had intruſted him with, ſhould be a means to make the Committee fall lower in their conditions. And though the Copy of this Letter came to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and was known by the Committee of Eſtates before they fell upon their Inſtructions, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of all this, theſe who had projected the buſineſs would go on, and did proſecute it with ſo much heat and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs, that the buſineſs, both in Inſtructions and Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93569:8"/>was concluded by the Committee of Eſtates, although the Parliament were to ſit down vvithin four or five dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Thoſe of you that were upon publique buſineſs, may remember how the whole matter was carried, being hudled over, and over-haſted, ſo as might have rendred the buſineſſe ſuſpitious to any that were not much left of God; to ſome it did clearly appear to be carryed on by way of deſigne. Though the ſhenning of ſcandall made ſome honeſt men go along in it; yet I think that which partly did entangle ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, was the expectation they had that the King would not agree to the Inſtructions. As for the carrying on of the Treaty, and the managing of it in <hi>Holland,</hi> I refer that to the cauſes of the Commiſſions Faſt appointed when they ſate at <hi>Sterling,</hi> and to the Weſtland Remonſtrances of Kirk and Army.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My deſigne</hi> in all this is, that you may take notice how a party and faction, even of thoſe whom the Lord had ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the reſt of the Nation (pretending as highly as ever) has carried aſide and entangled the Godly, and undermmed you. And when in part your ſnare is diſcovered unto you (though with the price of many ſorrows to your ſelves and much miſery to the Land) now they begin to appear in their own colours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My dear Friends,</hi> Give me leave in a Chriſtian freedom to expoſtulate with you, and from what I have laid down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, either as matter of Fact, or as your received prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, to ſpeak freely my own heart unto you, what my thoughts reach unto, concerning your preſent low condition, as what may have had a great hand in the Providence of God to make your condition as it is. I think it may appear unto you from what hath been ſaid (though I ſhould adde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing) that there is a diſtinct intereſt of the People of God, from all worldly intereſts; that it does alſo clearly appear, that your mingling yours therewith, and your complying and joyning with Malignant and carnall Inſtruments, in proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof hath had no ſmall influence in bringing you to ſo low a condition as you are at this day. Yea, and which is a greater abomination, and alſo exceedingly tending thereto, when you and your brethren in <hi>England</hi> did fall into miſtakes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93569:8"/>and differences together, have you not ſtrengthened the hands of your and their enemies by declaring one anothers Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the world, and not only ſo; Have not you, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, ſided with the men of the world, in their way of reproaching your Brethren, Yea, have not you made them Judges of the differences between you and them, which is contrary to that of the Apoſtle, even in Civill things betwixt ſuch as are Saints indeed, that they ſhould not bring their cauſes before the Heathen Judges, much leſs their ſpiritual differences? And whether the generality of the Parliament and General Aſſembly of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath been any other, upon a true accompt, but heathen Iudges (in reſpect of the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of God in them in their publick actings or private wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings) I leave it to your ſerious conſideration. And I appeal to your ſelves, whether you have not in an implicite way, for the moſt part, f llowed their Iudgements, eſpecially the Kirk, and how (by ſo doing) you have been entangled and enſnared (if you will not ſee) you ſhall ſee.</p>
            <p>Conſider how the Lord condiſcends to your weakneſs, by writing in great Letters your ſin and your ſnare in theſe, by diſcovering to you what I have aſſerted both of Kirk and State: You are not ſtrangers to proceedings at St. <hi>Johnſton,</hi> how theſe men are now not aſhamed to profeſs their wayes before the Sun, all their fair pretences, whereby they have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared you, are now coming out in their own colours: I need not name the particulars, they being ſo evident; theſe men that have heightened prejudices between you and your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>England</hi> upon fair pretences, who were Iudges and Parties, whoſe guilty conſcierces told them, they deſerv'd to be ſo dealt with, as their brethren had been dealt with by the Godly in <hi>England,</hi> whom the Lord had ſo ſtrangely raiſed up for that Work, and did clearly ſee they ſhould be ſo dealt with by you, when you ſhould come to underſtand your own intereſt, and the true intereſt of that which you had primarily engaged your ſelves unto: And therefore notwithſtanding they did make uſe of you, and did entangle you with good pretences, yet your ſelves know they were always jealous of you, and did hate you in their hearts; and for the Kirk, what
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93569:9"/>they are become (I mean the generality of them) how great Traitors to their own Profeſſions and Declarations, Preachings, Warnings, and Remonſtrances, &amp; to the intereſt of all the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Scotland</hi>) is evident (paſsing all other things) by their ſenſe of the Weſtland Remonſtrance, and their going along with that Parliament at St. <hi>Iohnſton,</hi> and by their late Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Remonſtrances, Declarations and Acts, and all theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of good Patriots, which is an evidence, that their intereſt is worldly, and not Spirituall, and hath the Mark of the Beaſt upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear Freinds,</hi> I humbly ſuppoſe it does not become you to be implicite in receiving any thing of conſequence from the beſt of men, much leſs from ſuch as theſe have been and are, ye who have Ieſus Chriſt to be your Light and Councellor, and the anointing from above, and ſhould know that all men are lyars, and ready to be byaſſed with Intereſt, How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſeeming is it for you, eſpecially in theſe days, to be impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite in your belief, or in receiving any thing off mans hand, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out examination: How much this hath prevailed amongſt you, and how ye have loved tohave it ſo, is obvious, and how theſe lords over the conſcience, have purſued its being ſo, as hath alſo appeared in their peremptorineſs in acts queſtionable in themſelves, their naming all the Engliſh Army Sectaries and Blaſpemous, without exceptions, Enemies to the People of God and to godlineſs, Their bitter way of expreſsing of this, without (clearly or ſcarce at all) refuting their Error, or ſhewing what they held, their laboring to wreſt every thing to the worſt ſence, or to put ſuch a conſtruction, for the which there was not the leaſt ſhaddow of a ground, their giving it as the note of a Sectary in him that ſhould queſtion their way in theſe, or ſhould forbear to go along with them, or ſhould queſtion the matter, or whether that which they did aſſert to be Error, was ſo or no, calling theſe problematique queſtions, tending to rend the Church: and for Profeſſors, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it be a duty preſcribed unto, and commended in the people of God, eſpecially into a day of darkneſs and difficulty, to ſpeak often one to another, to exhort, to rebuke, to be free one with another; yet I appeal to one and all of you, if their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93569:9"/>hath not been, and is ſuch a ſpirit even amongſt you, that you could not, nor cannot bear any thing differing from your own opinion (or rather the opinion of the Kirk) whether in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Diſcipline, or the buſineſs of the time, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt of you (give me leave in Chriſtian freedom to ſpeak without offence) could not give a reaſon for what you held or practiſed, eſpecially in theſe things relating to the times, but were implicitely led by other mens judgements, which is your reproach, your ſin and your ſnare this day, and hath not had (I dare confidently ſay it) the leaſt hand in bringing you into the poſture you are at preſent: Doth not the language of all theſe, call upon you to ſeperate from world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intereſts and carnal men as much as you can, and from an implicite, carnal blinde way of fearing or truſting man? Is it not evident, that it hath been the deſign of God from the beginning of this work to have it ſo? Have not all his diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations from time to time ſignified this? yea, does not (as hath been ſaid) your own principles and practices hold out ſo much? Hath not your oppoſing of this (by your laboring to joyn the ſeed of the Woman and of the Serpent together, and to min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle their Intereſts) again and again brought contempt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment upon you? Have they not conſtantly (pretend what they will) laid you by, and ſet up themſelves? (and if this hold in Civil things, how much more in Spiritual) And do not you clearly ſee it cannot be otherwiſe? Is it not as clear as the light, that if this Parliament at St. <hi>Johnſton</hi> were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and another called according to the Laws of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, I dare ſay, and it is known to you, it might well be worſe, it could not be better, the reſult of ſo many years profeſsing and fighting for a Covenant (chiefly relating to Religion) a Nation wholly almoſt overgrown with Malignants, Enemies to you, and to what the Covenant chiefly drives at.</p>
            <p>And for the Kirk, I offer it to your conſideration, whether the generality of them be not godleſs, ſelf-ſeeking men, I do not onely mean this Commiſsion that goes along with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State, but any Aſſembly that hath been, or is likely to be in haſte; and for ſuch as are godly, I ſhall wiſh that too many (even of theſe) have not more an eye to the upholding of an
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93569:10"/>Arbitrary Power, unto their medling in Civil matters, then to the holding forth of Ieſus Chriſt, and the intereſt of the People of God: Hath it not been a ſnare to themſelves, and to all honeſt men in <hi>Scotland,</hi> eſpecially to ſuch as were in Iudicatories and Armies, Miniſters (though good men) medling ſo much in the buſineſs of the time, their way being when they were diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the State, to declare out of the Pulpits their faults, as alſo to put forth Declarations thereanent, which at the beſt did tend to nothing but to make the State Hypocrites, and to the deceiving of themſelves and all honeſt men, for the State ſeeing their way (in preaching and declaring againſt them) to tend much to the weakning of their Authority and Deſigns, did ſtudy how to carry on their Deſigns with the faireſt outſide that might be: I ſhall give one particular inſtance, which is this, their forcing of the King to ſubſcribe (paſsing all their former and late proceedings with him, and with the State) that Declaration, wherein he declares all the freinds of the Covenant to be his freinds, and the enemies thereof to be his: What a ſtrange way that was for them to draw up a Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that nature, and to compel him to ſubſcribe it, by a Declaration of abandoning his intereſt, if he ſhould refuſe to do it, I leave to the ſerious conſideration of all godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Profeſſors; and what hath been the ſad conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of proceedings in this kinde, and I hope it will not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as if I ſpoke againſt good men, whom I honor, or againſt the Miniſtry, my deſire being onely to take notice of thoſe things whereby they have wronged themſelves and the people of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My dear Friends,</hi> It doth more then evidently appear, that upon all the conſiderations ſpoken of, you muſt either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon your own Intereſt, and all you have been fighting, wreſtling and praying for, or elſe you muſt (as the people of God) and only upon that accompt, owne what is your own Intereſt, and the true Intereſt of that which is the Work in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in following the Lamb in his quarrell againſt the Beaſt, in cruſhing, oppoſing, daſhing in pieces, laying aſide, and tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon every thing that ſtands in the way of his exalting in the midſt of his People, or would uphold falſe Chriſts in more
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93569:10"/>or leſſe the power of the Beaſt, whether it be King or Kingneſs or Parliaments, or Intereſts of Nations, or Governments, or be it what it will: Oh if you were once joyned together upon this accompt, how ſhould you be made to revive, and your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach taken away? let it not be a ſtumbling-block in your way, that thus did the Sectaries (ſo called) in <hi>England,</hi> I do not queſtion, but the Lord in his preſent diſpenſations is letting you ſee your ſin and error in condemning your Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> for that which materially (at leaſt) was and is your Dutie: what better was their condition there, or in probability would have been then yours, had not the Lord raiſed up their Spirits to the conſideration of the continual hazard they were expoſed to, by ſuffering their Intereſt to be managed by a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of men, who minded not the Intereſt of the People of God, nor the true Intereſt of the Nation, and were upon the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a Treatie, wherein they were to give up the Intereſt of the Godly, and what they had been fighting for, to the will and power of him who was the greateſt Delinquent in the three Kingdomes, till (I ſay) the Lord raiſed up their Spirits to be inſtrumentall, in laying aſide thoſe unſuitable dangerous Inſtruments, and to perſecute all that has follow'd upon't, wherein how they have been countenanced and carryed through, is obvious: And truly I am perſwaded, that ill the Lord ſhall be pleaſed to open your eyes (as I hope he will) to ſee it your dutie to take the like courſe, and to ſee yours and their Intereſt to be one, and your Enemies one, (though your differences in ſome things ſhould continue) till ſomething of both theſe, ye ſhall be haunted with ſorrowes, and diſtreſſes, and diſappointments, and diſaſters one after another, (let me ſay this without offence) I am far from juſtifying thoſe in <hi>England,</hi> in al the circumſtances either of their way there, or of their coming into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſhall not ſay, but that there has been not onely an offence taken by you, but alſo an offence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, eſpecially in the way of their coming into <hi>Scotland,</hi> though they have this to ſay for themſelves; Firſt, that a Treatie was denyed, unleſſe they would deny the capacitie they ſtood into, and the reſolved deſperate carrying on the Treatie with the King, notwithſtanding all the diſcoveries of him and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93569:11"/>of his deſignes; and our example eleven years ago, who entered <hi>England</hi> with an Army for matters meerly concerning <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> without any call from any Publique Judicatories, and yet were owned by the Godly in <hi>England,</hi> and that during the time of the Treatie, an about, and after the cloſe of it, Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> was at Sea robbing their Ships, deſtroying their Trade by vertue of this Kings Commiſſions, <hi>Ormond</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> in the Head of the Popiſh Army, and ſeverall Commiſſions iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued forth to ſeverals in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> If you can look upon them as Brethren (as I am ſure they are at leaſt the generalitie of the leading, counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Partie, and ſuch as are Godly that adhere to them) It is your dutie to forgive and forget, though they have done you an Injury. They ſay, you have wronged them, and yet they profeſſe themſelves not only willing to forgive you, but to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low you with all kindneſs and reſpect, and to be uſefull to you, though it were by laying their Bones in the duſt for you. If there be Differences amongſt you, can there be no mids but to deſtroy one another? this ſeemes to be a ſtrange Paradox and device of Sathan, that you think you cannot ſtand except they fall, they do not think ſo, they profeſſe themſelves not onely willing, but deſirous, that your intereſt, as the Godly in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhould ſtand, though you ſhould differ in judgement from them: Can Chriſt's Kingdom be divided againſt it ſelf, truely it is nothing of Chriſt that would labour to divide his People in affections, and will plead their deſtroying one of another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> remember their profeſſions of love to you when they came into this Nation, and what a bitter return was made to them in your name: what a Chriſtian reply from them, what a meeting from you, and how unwilling they were the Buſines ſhould be decided by blood, and how blood-thirſty you were (bear the expreſſion) none more earneſt upon fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then you, notwithſtanding all their continuing their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of love, and their moderate carrying of themſelves in the Countrey, and their returning in their way towards <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> how eager were even you the Godly in their purſuit, how did you long for their ruine (whoſe preſervation I dare ſay, as Inſtruments, was and is yours) and did conclude them all men
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93569:11"/>ruined and broken, whom the Lord would in an outward way own no more: after the Lord had made you flee before them, (they being neceſſitated to fight, being environ'd upon <hi>All hands</hi>) yet notwithſtanding all the advantage they had, did they not follow you as much as ever, and ra her more? And the Lord having in a ſingular way ſeparated you from that Crew ye were intangled vvith, and ye beginning to ſee the errors of former vvays in ſome things at leaſt, and being in a Capacitie to owne your Intereſt, and diſ-ſatisfied in vvhat had formerly bin the ſtate of the Quarrel, and vvith the State and the Treatie at <hi>Breda,</hi> and your Brethren in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevved their Profeſsions of love to you, and their deſire to confer vvith you, and to have a ceſſation of Armes, and to ſome of you, having gone a great length in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, to evidence the realitie of their Profeſsions of Love, and after the State and Kirk had in ſuch a way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt your Remonſtrance, and though in it you had taken away that which was poſitively and unqueſtionably the ſtate of the Quarrell, and had (to my nderſtanding) put nothing in the room of it, yet your deſire to fight with them was ſo great, notwithſtanding of all theſe, that before you ſhould miſſ an opportunity, ye would rather fall in upon their Quarters upon the Lords day morning: And how ſtrangely ye were broken, and what were the particular remarkable paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, they know beſt that were there onely it is generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marked, that at <hi>Muſleburgh,</hi> at <hi>Dunbar</hi> and at <hi>Hamilton,</hi> the honeſt men got the ſaddeſt blows. However, they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue their profeſſions of Love to you, even to this day, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of all they have met with from you then, and I dare ſay from knowledge, that ſince <hi>Hamilton,</hi> if it had pleaſed the Lord to have opened your eyes to have known what was truly your intereſt &amp; your duty, it might have been in the power of the Godly of <hi>Scotland,</hi> not onely to have preſerved their own intereſt, but the intereſt of the Nation: and if it ſhould yet pleaſe the Lord to open your eyes, I am very confident it ſhould not only tend to your good, but to the good of the Land, and to the rectifying and compoſing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent differences and diſtances, and perhaps the Lords de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93569:12"/>is to make each of you uſefull in convincing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the extreams that either of you (it may be) hath been inclining to, if ye were once together as Brethren, Conferring Exhorting, Reproving, and Watching over each other, and Forbearing, Forgiving, and Loving each other, and not as Enemies, reproaching, contemning, ſmiting, taking advantage, raiſing and fomenting prejudices one againſt another. <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> I hope you will not be offended with my Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which is, not to lay open your nakedneſs, but to ſhew the kindneſs &amp; tendernſs of theſe whom ye have looked upon as your Enemies, that ye maybe perſwaded to meet them with the like: Sure I am it is the Deſigne of God, to have his People one, &amp; to cauſe them follow him together with one heart, at leaſt it is his promiſe it ſhall be ſo; And that the <hi>Whore that ſits upon the many waters ſhall be deſtroyed, and that the Kingdoms of the world ſhall become the Kingdoms of his Son,</hi> and I hope he will not looſe you, even to make you inſtrumentall in this great Work he is about, for it is his time to build up <hi>Zion,</hi> not to deſtroy her, nor no part of her, and if it were not for this, I ſhould have been laid by from medling into any buſineſs ſo weighty as this is: I know it is ſuch a way, as the way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring man, though a fool cannot erre therein.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93569:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
